let us bring them on the show everybody
they we we're going to talk mainly about
pan quake and the importance of pan
quake and
uh we wanted to bring
both of these gentlemen back on the show
they've both been on the show before um
first of all
uh xcia and whistleblower john kariaka
was here who uh let's bring him on the
show john how are you hey doing well
thanks graham sorry to hear about
youtube man not good
well dude that's
this is happening to everybody i know
it's awful sorry
i know it's great i mean it's it's it's
it's insane i mean it's happened on
youtube i mean
i i have several friends and i'm sure
you'd know people too worked at rt
america so they just basically wiped rt
america off the face of the earth i mean
like just like that it's and all these
really good shows redacted tonight on
contact boom bust max kaiser all these
shows that i watched um that
brought news and information to people
in a way that the amer american media
isn't it's just it's
awful
terrible
we live we live in we live in a crazy
we live in crazy times um yeah
but uh we'll bring also on uh
the cso of pan quake who's been on the
show before mr sean o'brien sean how you
doing
uh great happy to be here
excellent
well um
let's get right into it uh
about
first of all where pan quake is it's
just i mean it's close to being done
i've talked to susie about it uh
and then i want to really get into the
importance of it
especially
to what we were just talking about john
and i were just talking about and all
the censorship all of us have seen
so
why don't sean why don't you just give
us sort of an update of where it's at
and the status of it and then we'll get
into the the reasons why
sure so um as a lot of your audience
knows pancreatic.com is a short
messaging service um we've been um
working on it uh from a development
standpoint since approximately last
summer
and stuff is moving very very quickly
the development process is going really
fast
we just revealed to the world um the
look and feel so the
beautiful screens um showing what a
pancake dashboard will look like um this
environment that we want folks to um be
happy living in
um expressing themselves sharing
information you know um and having a
network where they really can feel and
know actually transparently that they're
reaching the folks that they intend to
reach they have the amplification they
should have that they have the voice
that they should have
on social media um so we have uh you
know a functioning uh interface uh john
has seen it and we have demoed it to
some other folks as well um we're
constantly uh building and adding to
that um and we're push push pushing so
we're in the last phase of our crowd
fundraiser so we're a crowdfunding model
here um we've had you know approximately
3 500 folks donate to that crowdfunder
which is just incredible um and we need
to get through this last phase get
across the goal line um so we can bring
the folks we need to bring in for things
like support um making sure we have real
humans and not algorithms right
um who are going to help our folks um
you know if they if they need that that
support uh in the network um
and just upping the business really yeah
and just for people look here i've just
put this is what the interface looks
like i've seen it as well it's pretty
amazing uh to see how functional it is
and then to just go back to uh
this is how many people have donated
thus far this is the campaign
uh and
this is
to me already showing
how hungry everybody is for this and and
what it's going to do and it was really
sort of exciting
um
[Music]
for me and for myself for all of us to
to see this one of the things that i
find exciting about it is
that um
you know as a stand-up comedian just to
somebody that that promotes shows i've
been so
um
you know throttled that that i you know
i've amassed followers on all these
social media platforms and then i tell
them
hey i'm coming to your town to perform
or watch my live stream or whatever and
they're like never heard of it they're
not even allowed to hear of it so it's
really just just as a performer not to
mention
uh all the other reasons for
to use it for censorship but um
i want to
like
so john
what what drew you to this project and
how do you see it yeah um
how do you see it interacting with the
intelligence community which which
really has hijacked so many of these
social media platforms
really great questions this is the best
way to open this conversation what what
drew me was several different things
actually um number one i've gotten to
the point where i have to go to my
twitter every day to see if they've put
a little red tag saying that i'm a
an official mouthpiece of the russian
government which i'm not but
i mean poor ed schultz has been dead for
how many years and they made him a they
put a tag on him saying that he's a
mouthpiece of the russian government so
that was one thing that bothers me very
much more importantly though
you know i i used to go to twitter
constantly
to read the news
what what i would do is
because i can't read everything as much
as i would like to
i would follow people that i respect
from a wide variety of backgrounds and
look all day long to see what they're
posting what's ralph nader saying right
what's uh uh the the marshall uh
center saying or the brennan center
or propublica
and now it's
you know so much of what i used to be
interested in is banned
or it's you can't see you can't find
telesur you can't find rt or sputnik uh
any anything that i'm interested in that
has to do with prison reform for example
uh is deemed to be anti-american
and so all of a sudden i just can't read
the news anymore facebook's even worse
facebook beat twitter to the punch
they're even worse
and then about a year ago susie dawson
approached me and told me about pan
quake and the idea behind pan quake was
no corporate money no government money
no advertising completely open source
code so that everything is transparent
and i mean like in the literal sense of
the word it's transparent there is
there is no
big brother
to
go through
our our uh
posts and then
impose an algorithm on us that's going
to decide what our friends and followers
can see and what they can't see
so
you know we we give a lot of
we give a lot of lip service grabbed to
to freedom of speech
and to transparency and
nine times out of ten at least here in
the united states with these corporate
run sites we're just not serious about
it
well what
told me that that pan quake was serious
about it was the fact that it's hosted
in iceland which i absolutely love
so it's not subject to a national
security letter from the fbi
demanding all of your user data and all
this other nonsense that we see all the
time in the news
and because there are no
um outside investors no corporations or
governments or think tanks or anything
else
there's no pressure to squelch free
speech
so this in my view is what these big
tech
platforms
originally thought they wanted to be
and then realized that they could never
be
never
yeah and they've i mean you you
especially you read a book like uh you
know when when google met wikileaks you
know you realize that like google has
been basically doing data collection for
the intelligence community for quite a
while so it's absolutely absolutely you
know i remember oh it's been 10 or 12
years now when uh somebody i don't know
who somebody leaked to wikileaks that it
wasn't just google it was literally
every one of the big tech firms from
from microsoft to google to apple to all
the big communications companies every
last one of them
was providing information to the cia
into nsa and to the fbi with these
national security letters well you have
to ask yourself when the director of
security
for microsoft
is the former station chief well i
shouldn't say where he was the station
chief but
you know there's a problem there's a
problem with this how do we trust this
company
well
i can trust
yeah and that's the thing that's so
fascinating to me is like in in you know
in and how susie's explained it to me
and to all of us like i'm you know i'm
not a coder i'm not a tech guy at all
and so
the questions that have come up like
um
and because susie's been targeted
herself and because she
knew julian and and understands how this
works
they put in you guys have put in so much
stuff to
prevent all of this like the iceland
thing i never even would have thought of
that you know like and the the the
servers are not amazon servers because
that's boom they can they can just call
up amazon say shut it down and it's done
and
jeff bezos has got 600 million dollars
from the cia so we
know we know where where was that
so
um
i want to like uh some of the questions
and sean i know you can you can answer
these
um
the questions of like
can it be
hacked can it be can can somebody just
come in and buy pan quake and and snatch
up all your data it is always all the
data going to be stored somewhere so
everyone can steal it or hack it or
whatever can you answer those questions
for anybody
sure um and first i just want to say you
know the points you're making and the
the way we're talking about this is
absolutely correct right um we want to
be a lifeboat away from big tech and
that's you know an analogy of course but
it's a one we really really mean
um protecting data is actually
protecting lives um you know especially
when we're talking about you know high
value targets for the cia etc etc um
activists um who are making an impact
right there they know that they're being
targeted it has a real effect on their
lives and these other social media sites
that are advertising surveilling you
know creating these frameworks which
were in turn work with these state
agencies um they are exposing people to
real harm and real danger so um that's
exactly the thing that we care about um
you know protecting people from
and that's why we're building things the
way we're building them so
on the building piece um so yeah we have
our core infrastructure in iceland um
it's a good jurisdiction for you know
freedom of speech and a number of other
protections from
specifically the us government but other
governments as well um but also we have
a decentralized model right we have a
blockchain based model and our
nodes the machines the people right with
smartphones and desktop computers and so
on that will be in pancake.com those
folks will be communicating to each
other using peer-to-peer connections
right so we're making sure we're using
the edge of the network we're having
folks
uh communicate in a decentralized not
cloud computing way um and that
in turn makes a network very resilient
against things like you know ddosing and
other kinds of attacks that could bring
it down right um we spread out the
computing as far as we possibly can um
we make sure we have strong encryption
strong um you know authentication and
verification of users between other
users and we have some clever encryption
where we're uh implementing to do all of
that
um we make sure that uh we have open
source code right so we're gonna release
uh
with the pan quake launch we're gonna
release the code for the entire stack um
that means anybody can review and audit
that and we will have the best and
brightest security experts and already
do have quite a few um looking at that
work looking at that code um so that's
our sort of the fundamental things but
if you care about protecting data right
don't take that data in in the first
place okay one of the analogies that a
lot of security experts talk about is
data as what they call a toxic asset
and that means basically you know the
more data you collect the more you sort
of put it on a shelf somewhere it's like
a corroding battery that just gets worse
and worse and worse
these other services right that we're so
used to using on the internet have these
huge databases these huge server farms
that have all this information on their
users all these profiles and so on um at
pan quake right we don't want that data
in the first place okay
anything that's even remotely sensitive
will be on your machine so we're
architecting it so that you have a user
data store on your devices um and that's
your data you own it we don't want it um
you're not even collecting the data
right that's right that's exactly right
so
you don't even
it's incredible right yeah it's
incredible i love it you know but it's
so simple really and and you know we're
not going to collect email addresses or
phone numbers or those kinds of things
that folks are now having to use all the
time to verify themselves on these other
networks
we don't want it right
that's good for us right and it's good
for you um and that's that's the basic
principle there um the nuts and bolts of
how it works i mean we're taking some
very clever pieces of software some very
clever encryption um we're
decentralizing and spreading things out
like true peer-to-peer networks um we're
doing a lot of the things which you know
other transformative you know um apps
are doing um to change the the world and
this thing that some folks are starting
to call web three right although we'll
see if that catches on um but the point
is you know it's about breaking down
these control structures breaking down
the centralization of the network
environment that we have which is what
allows the googles etc etc to have the
censorship that they have but it also
allows them right to basically ruin
people's lives by amassing these huge
profiles on people and then following
them throughout their entire childhood
now i mean the people who've grown up in
this environment all the way through you
know they hope that you know the end of
their lives that's that's the google
plan right um and that's something we
not only would never do we don't want to
do it um and because we're not focusing
on spying on people right like these
other companies are and they put all
this engineering effort into trying to
figure out who people are and who
they're talking to and how to stop them
from talking to specific people or stop
them from sharing different information
that takes a lot of engineering work
right um because we're not doing all
that we can use our engineering muscle
right to deliver something different
that allows information to be amplified
freely allows you to reach your audience
and know verifiably and transparently
with the blockchain record that you're
reaching your audience and so on and so
forth um it's
it's simple right it's it's in some ways
going back to you know the better part
of the internet before it was destroyed
in the last you know 10 15 20 years by
these big tech companies and we're using
the lessons and the cool technology
that's out now to reinvent that internet
into something that's better and more
powerful so
well that's
yeah that's got to have them all
befuddled because you're not creating
something to try to take over the world
and become billionaires and build rocket
ships to fly away from a planet that you
let set on fire um so i wanted to
and since we've all said we've all seen
you know how they've used infiltrated
social media like the intelligence and
stuff to to blow up activist movements
there's you see these infiltrators you
know they'll have a pro a profile that
you know
you look to read the boy they seem like
they're a real true lefty activist it
says free assange and medicare for all
or whatever else and then they're always
like stirring up or whatever
um
so i wanted to
sean
quickly tell us like
how that works in terms of the
the giving someone a pan quake and
giving them the authority to do that so
that even because because the question
is like okay so you guys are doing five
dollars a month subscription what's to
prevent google or the cia or whomever to
buy a bunch of bot accounts and then
they can just take this thing over and
in six months to a year it'll be ruined
again just like the last cool thing we
thought was going to be great that's not
ruined
sure sure um so there's a few mechanisms
that we're sort of building in at a
fundamental level we'll obviously also
have checks and balances uh you know um
intrusion detection systems and so on so
that we can start spotting you know real
attacks on the network but putting aside
that technical stuff um first off the
subscriber model is a good way to limit
um things like botnets like all these
bots um you know swarming and creating
these you know what used to be called
egg accounts on twitter right these
these bs accounts with 30 followers that
just harass people and and make people's
lives miserable um that subscription
actually does help to limit that
somewhat um you know the types of tools
that you know the cia the nsa uses to
spin up these fake personas as they call
them in their own documents um
that is not going to be easy to do um
when you have a subscription model so
that's that's sort of the first thing
right yes i guess really if they want to
buy a bunch of bots well that's thanks
for the five bucks from all these robots
right that's one way to think about it
do they really want to be funding us
right
so
at any rate um
the second part is that um it's an
opt-in
social network in the sense that you're
going to see content from the people you
follow or content for example that you
might search for so if you search for
cats you're going to see cats right um
that's not a very effective network for
spies to use to amplify content and
manipulate people right
because what they rely upon is spinning
up these you know groups of fake
accounts so that they can basically push
their narrative so that they can have
you know these fake trolling
conversations shove things into people's
timelines manipulate um on the back end
when they can the algorithm to silence
some voices and to allow some other
voices to be bigger so that their voices
the bots that they control the paid
staff that they pay to manipulate social
feeds those folks suddenly have a huge
voice in these big tech networks right
none of that's going to be possible in
pan quake
folks have a level playing field which
is very big to us and it's not just
about you know the spies and all of that
which certainly is a problem that we're
well well aware of um but we want to be
somebody who's you know just um starting
out uh trying to promote content such as
yourself graham i mean you're not just
starting out but you would be when you
get into pancake new there um we want
you to have equal footing to you know
if i don't know somebody who was uh some
huge star came into the network right
we want to know that those accounts
start out
on equal footing have the ability to
amplify have the ability to reach their
followers and folks will find that they
have a voice that where they don't feel
like they're you know in some sort of
popularity contest right um
a lot of that again is just about not
manipulating timelines right not
manipulating content not forcing fake
trends into people's faces that are
advertising the next disney thing
um we're not doing any of that but that
that also makes it so that a lot of the
abuse a lot of the things that facebook
especially has been called out for um
can't happen in the network um if you're
not manipulating algorithms you know to
do this terrible stuff to do you know
manipulation of uh political beliefs for
you know some sort of political campaign
and so on and so forth um
then you know uh
there's there's a lot less to worry
about as far as folks who are worried
about you know these kinds of uh um i
don't know these social uh uh
engineers let's say
uh
if we get us you know uh someone in
there who is trying to manipulate people
they're going to find it's going to be
very very difficult with the way that
we're just having opt-in content no
trend manipulation no timeline
manipulation and honest transparency
about statistics um that alone is going
to make it really hard for these folks
to operate the way that they're used to
operating in the big tech environment
yeah and so let me ask you this john so
like you've obviously experienced first
hand the targeting for being a
whistleblower you've seen it
you know the assange movement the
wikileaks has been targeted i mean susie
dawson just put in the chat how
they shut down the paypal donations
during the fundraising of this and so
how do you what what i mean like we have
to think in these terms and this is the
thing i liked and the conversations i
had with susie is she's assuming these
attacks are going to come she's not like
let's hope they play nice we know
they're not going to play nice we know
what they're going to do so what attack
what things do you see
them trying to do to shut down pan quake
john and how do you see pan quake being
able to with withstand these attacks
um yeah you know i'm confident that
susie and sean and the team
have foreseen
uh a lot of what uh we ought to be
expecting basing basing the the servers
in iceland i think was a stroke of
genius
even the corporate headquarters is um is
offshore in a in a place that's very
secure for this kind of thing
very very forward thinking um
if i were still at the cia or nsa i
would be looking for a technical way in
i think that the fact that
there's this subscription service which
makes it almost impossible to create
bots to attack the system unless the
bots
pay
you know the five dollars a month
was also uh brilliant uh what the cia
well i would expect different things
from the cia from nsa nsa i would expect
technical attacks and bill benny bill
benny's on the team bill can go into
some deep detail on that kind of thing
he's he's a genius
on the cia side i would expect um
a different kind of underhandedness i
would expect uh personal attacks on pan
quake's leadership i would i would
expect um uh
articles uh condemning
all of us who are involved for whatever
reason oh john kiriakou he's a convicted
felon
you want to be in business with a
convicted felon you know i get that all
the time from people who can't debate on
the issues
so uh
you know what they did to to wikileaks
uh allowed us to learn
lessons and we've been able to safeguard
ourselves to protect ourselves from
those kinds of attacks it's going to be
much much harder to attack pan quake
than it is to attack wikileaks and
because pan quake is still so small it's
still you know in its nascent stages
i think we largely haven't come to their
attention yet
and i'm i'm optimistic that once we do
come to their attention once we're big
enough or important enough to be worth
attacking
will be
so ready for them that there won't be
anything that they can do
well yeah i mean it will get i can't
wait for the article that pat quake is
helping putin or whatever whatever that
happened and you know it's coming
you know
they're gonna hashtag putin quake or
whatever right
quake great yeah just like just like ed
snowden defected to russia like nobody
in america remembers that he was in the
transit lounge when john kerry revoked
his passport so yeah histories change as
time passes it's going to be up to us to
make sure that the truth is out there
which again pancake will afford us that
safe place to do it and i want people to
understand that
this wasn't just like something slapped
together you've got bill benny involved
nsa whistleblower john you're a cia
whistleblower involved you've got susie
who's been targeted you've got people
who played this game
and see the tactics and so
you know let's all just be ready for the
whatever pan quake kills puppies
headline from cnn or whatever whatever
whatever exactly
that's how you know you're making an
impact right yeah how else are you gonna
attack the former number four at nsa
nsa's technical director who's arguably
one of the
the greatest minds in america on the
issue of internet security and privacy
how else are you going to attack him
right yeah you've got to say he he he
killed christmas or whatever
bill benny hates rainbows or whatever
they're gonna whatever they're gonna say
um so um and i the thing too i want i
want to
talk about this as well uh because susie
one of the things our conversation her
and i had was about
she wants to be ready
to have staff in place so that if it
takes off it's not overwhelmed because
that's another thing too we get all of a
sudden you know two million people sign
up for this thing in in 20 days oh we
don't we don't know we don't have the
staff in place to do that so what what
steps are you guys taking in case that
which is which would be a good problem
to have
um for that to be handled
so we have a staggered release model
right um so first i just want to say you
know if you folks are interested in our
progress and how we're building in in
the direction we're moving in and why
we're making certain choices and so on
we do monthly delivery meetings um where
we recap basically everything that
happened in the month both the technical
stuff and the non-technical um and we
just make sure we have that transparency
for all of our donors and the public in
general um but yeah uh we do staggered
releases basically so uh first off uh we
are having a beta right and that beta
will have 5 000 users in it if folks
would like to apply to potentially be
someone who can join the beta
you can go out to pancreatic.com there's
a link to apply to join the beta we just
want to make sure we do a little bit of
vetting and and we don't have bots
warming us at the beginning all right so
that's the kind of thing we're being
smart about and and that that model is
very smart um that way um and not just
bots but you know disruptive folks and
so we want to have we like disruptive
folks of a certain kind but we
we want to have trustworthy folks in the
network who really care about what we're
doing and and uh and so on and so forth
that's a smart thing to do
and then we go to the 1.1
and we're going to get to uh 25 000
users for that release um so we're just
having just a little bit larger for that
and then we will open it to the public
and have sort of this staggered release
model that allows us to make sure
especially with a blockchain right we
have to have that core of trust in the
beginning um the folks who are part of
what's called a consensus model and and
uh your audience who are cryptocurrency
folks i'm sure are familiar with this
kind of thing um you need to make sure
that that core is uh non-malicious
actors basically um so we have to have
that really trusted core of folks in the
beginning um and then we just sort of
move out and branch out the um support
plan which is something that the staff
is working on
in which i'm sure we will
talk about this month in the delivery
meeting and probably continue to talk
about um is very smart um we're making
sure that we're scaling and planning to
scale you know having real humans who
can help real people and um doing that
and making sure that's in place giving
people that different experience from
you know all this algorithmic you know
bs that they're used to um is also
really important to us right
we want people to be respected we're
building respect in
not just into the technology right but
also into the way that we're building
the infrastructure around that the human
infrastructure around that um so that's
that's really a big part of it but also
i will say like this decentralization
stuff right um which has already changed
the world with you know cryptocurrency
and and some other decentralized apps
that are out there d apps or whatever
folks want to call it um it's really
powerful it's really scalable
so we can plan sort of a staging of
bringing more and more nodes online
expanding the network out across
continents and so on and so forth
we're using the pipe in very efficient
ways so to speak right we're not just
funneling a bunch of data into a google
data center somewhere or relying upon
some amazon aws server that we're
renting you know that's not even ours
and that kind of thing allows us to
really plan in a smart way um
we don't want to be like some of these
networks that folks may be familiar with
the the getters which had you know
getter had all kinds of problems to put
it mildly on true social the the trump
network that
seems to have fallen apart before it
started barely um
that kind of thing are the mistakes that
we know well are well aware of and we
can make sure that we don't do
um but also i mean look we want to have
uh uh
something sustainable here um we're not
trying to as as we said you know have uh
vc money or corporate pr teams we don't
have corporate marketing teams
everything we've raised to this point is
graph grassroots money um from folks who
are donating their hard-earned cash to
us to do something amazing um and that's
been done you know with word of mouth
our word of mouth and speaking to each
other human to human is really really
powerful um so we have regular people
being our voice we're going to get that
critical mass and when we get there
right we get those folks on board and we
can't be ignored by the corporations and
these other folks you know that's when
you'll see the smear pieces certainly
but that's also when you're going to see
a situation where we can't be ignored
and we're on the front pages right um
you have to build it that way and that
that's a lesson really that you know we
learned in in some respect from from
wikileaks right um
they built something that couldn't be
ignored there um they were releasing
information that was vitally you know
important um and did it in such a clever
way especially with i mean with the
numerous releases that they did um
that you know even though the mainstream
media didn't want to report this stuff
they had to right and um that's sort of
the thing that we're learning and trying
to do with fan quick as well
we want to be something big
that people care about that people are
part of real ordinary folks and then you
know um
conquer the world let's hope we'll see
everybody thanks for watching we are
still in our like ninth month of
demonetization from youtube so support
what we're doing at patreon.com
gramelwood or rockfin.com graham ellwood
which is a blockchain cryptocurrency
platform
it's free to sign up and there's a
premium level at ten dollars a month and
for that you get everybody on the
platform's premium content myself lee
camp ron plecon jimmy dore whitney webb
kim iverson abby martin and many many
others you can also support what we're
doing at venmo at graham-elwood and go
to gramelwood.com we have a paypal
button and a p.o box i also have crypto
wallets which are all in the show notes
thanks for supporting what we do
you